Hello, I'm Tim Gipson and today I want to talk to you about carpenter safety.
So I've got a few things here that we're going to be looking at.
Now the most important thing is that when you are working on any kind of power tools or even hand tools and maybe even something as simple as hammering a nail.
The first and most important thing that you can have for safety gear is to have your safety glasses.
So - and if they're a little dirty you can clean them up... but you only have two eyes so you want to make sure you protect them.
Some other gear that you have if you are dealing with tickly dusty conditions which is you deal with a lot when any time you're doing any kind of construction is the dust mask.
Now these come in various types, this is just your basic dust mask.
You have others that actually are upgraded and can have respirators in them, or vent valves so that are used for more such things as paint, or fine particle sanding, such as in drywall.
And then the next article is protect your hands.
Having a good set of gloves, these are a heavy duty glove.
They are patterned for comfort.
And fit the size and protection your hands and your fingers from nicks and cuts.
This is a good step to have.
So glasses, safety dam.
Next thing I'm going to talk to you about is a table saw when we talk about safety in carpenter tools, a table saw is a good place to start.
Whether it's - this is a contractor's saw so it's one of the larger ones, but whether you're working with this type or even a small table saw type, the most important thing is to make sure you do proper things to ensure your safety.
This is the guard, now this is a standard guard that comes with any table saw, but whenever you are actually getting the act of sawing you want to make sure that's down.
Now whenever you do something on the blade, such as changing the blade, you want to make sure that you unplug, so never work on any power tool as far as changing the blades unless it's unplugged.
Here, I have a feather fence which is made and the feather fence will allow you to hold pieces against, so that will provide extra security in sawing.
And then you have other things such as push blocks, and a push stick.
These help you to guide things through, keeps your fingers away from the cutting surfaces.
So just some basic safety tips there and I'm Tim Gipson talking about carpenter safety.